Chapter 5. breakfast.
I quickly followed suit, and descending into the barroom, accosted the grinning
landlord very pleasantly. I cherished no malice toward him, though he had been
skyllocking with me not a little in the matter of my bedfellow. However, a good
laugh is a mighty good thing, and rather too scarce a good thing, the more the
pity. So if any one man in his own proper person affords stuff for a good
joke to anybody, let him not be backward, but let him cheerfully allow
himself to spend and be spent in that way. And the man that has anything
bountifully laughable about him, be sure there is more in that man than you
perhaps think for. The barroom was now full of the borders who had been
dropping in the night previous, and whom I had not as yet had a good look at.
They were nearly all whalemen, chief mates and second mates and third mates
and sea carpenters and sea coopers and sea blacksmiths and harpooners and
shipkeepers. A brown and brrawy company with bossy beards, an unshorn shaggy
set, all wearing monkey jackets for morning gowns. You could pretty plainly
tell how long each one had been ashore.
This young fellow's healthy cheek is like a suntoasted pear in hue and would
seem to smell almost as musky. He cannot have been three days landed from his
Indian voyage. That man next to him looks a few shades lighter. You might
say a touch of satin wood is in him. In the complexion of a third, still lingers
a tropic taawn, but slightly bleached with all. He doubtless has terried whole
weeks ashore. But who could show a cheek like Quiqu, which barred with various
tints seemed like the Andes western slope to show forth in one array
contrasting climates zone by zone.
Grubho, now cried the landlord, flinging open a door, and in we went to breakfast.
They say that men who have seen the world thereby become quite at ease in
manner, quite self-possessed in company.
Not always, though. Ledard, the great New England traveler, and Park,
the Scotch one. Of all men, they possess the least assurance in the parlor. But
perhaps the mere crossing of Siberia in a sledge drawn by dogs, as Ledger did,
or the taking of a long solitary walk on an empty stomach in the negro heart of
Africa, which was the sum of poor Mongo's performances. This kind of
travel, I say, may not be the very best mode of attaining a high social polish.
Still, for the most part, that sort of thing is to be had anywhere.
These reflections just here are occasioned by the circumstance that
after we were all seated at the table, and I was preparing to hear some good
stories about whailing, to my no small surprise, nearly every man maintained a
profound silence, and not only that, but they looked embarrassed. Yes, here were
a set of sea dogs, many of whom, without the slightest bashfulness, had boarded
great whales on the high seas, entire strangers to them, and duled them dead
without winking. And yet here they sat at a social breakfast table, all of the
same calling, all of kindred tastes, looking round as sheepishly at each
other, as though they had never been out of sight of some sheepfold among the
green mountains. A curious sight, these bashful bears, these timid warrior
whalemen. But as for Quiquague, why Quequ sat there among them at the head
of the table, too, it so chanced, as cool as an icicle. To be sure, I cannot
say much for his breeding. His greatest admirer could not have cordially
justified his bringing his harpoon into breakfast with him, and using it there
without ceremony, reaching over the table with it to the imminent jeopardy
of many heads, and grappling the beef stakes toward him. But that was
certainly very coolly done by him, and everyone knows that in most people's
estimation to do anything coolly is to do it gently.
We will not speak of all Que's peculiarities here, how he estued coffee
and hot rolls, and applied his undivided attention to beef stakes done rare
enough that when breakfast was over, he withdrew like the rest into the public
room, lighted his tomahawk pipe, and was sitting there quietly digesting and
smoking with his inseparable hat on when I sied out for a stroll.